<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>mac on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/mac/</link><description>Recent content in mac on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:34:16 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/mac/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Working with the M1 mac</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/m1-mac/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:34:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/m1-mac/</guid><description>After a bit of faffing around with invoicing and reimbursing, I have finally managed to get ahold of a machine specifically for work. At my company&amp;rsquo;s request, I have purchased a MacBook Pro with the Apple M1 chip.
Anybody who has read my blog knows I have significant misgivings about Apple, their products, and their business practices. I am generally not a fan of working with Macs, but I must confess I was intrigued to see how this new chip would perform.</description></item><item><title>Apple: drink the cider</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/apple-drink-cider/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/apple-drink-cider/</guid><description>Let me get this off my chest right now. I hate Apple. I hate iOS. I hate macOS. I hate the software, the hardware, and the ethos of Apple. To my mind, Apple represents the very worst of the technology industry: devices which are hard to use, easy to break, and difficult to fix. Therefore, I&amp;rsquo;m never surprised when I see news stories like this one.
The long and short of this story is that Apple have implemented a new chip (the T2 chip) which can detect whether or not repairs to a broken machine have been carried out by a verified technician using a pre-configured pin code.</description></item><item><title>Personal matters</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</guid><description>This post is more of a rant than anything technical. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s more of a moan born of recent frustrations. Nevertheless, this is my website. Where better to moan?
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started a new job working for a software company. My day-to-day work mostly includes rifling through SQL databases and making changes as well as searching for causes of issues faced by customers. This job has me using a work-issued MacBook Air and a copy of Windows 10 running in a virtual machine.</description></item></channel></rss>