<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>reviews on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/categories/reviews/</link><description>Recent content in reviews on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>Unless otherwise credited all material &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a> by Ciarán Ainsworth</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:34:16 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/categories/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Working with the M1 mac</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/m1-mac/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:34:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/m1-mac/</guid><description>After a bit of faffing around with invoicing and reimbursing, I have finally managed to get ahold of a machine specifically for work. At my company&amp;rsquo;s request, I have purchased a MacBook Pro with the Apple M1 chip.
Anybody who has read my blog knows I have significant misgivings about Apple, their products, and their business practices. I am generally not a fan of working with Macs, but I must confess I was intrigued to see how this new chip would perform.</description></item><item><title>Dell XPS 13 thoughts</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/xps-13-thoughts/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:28:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/xps-13-thoughts/</guid><description>So I decided finally (finally!) that I was going to invest in a new device in preparation for my upcoming move to Germany. I&amp;rsquo;ve never really been much of a hardware person, if I&amp;rsquo;m honest. Hardware has always just been a means to an end to get me working with software as efficiently as possible be it productivity software, games, or media software. For this reason my computers have always been a bit off the mark; I will nearly always pick something over-specced or under-specced, something too big or something too small, etc.</description></item><item><title>In defence of GNOME Web</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/in-defence-of-gnome-web/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/in-defence-of-gnome-web/</guid><description>So you probably already know that Mozilla recently went bang and fired 25% of its workforce before announcing that whoops lol actually we are still going to be able to feed the hungry fox this year. Among the teams affected were the servo developers, a lot of the threat response team, and (I believe) the entirety of the team behind MDN: the only good resource for web development don&amp;rsquo;t @ me.</description></item><item><title>Plan 9 fun</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/plan-9-fun/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/plan-9-fun/</guid><description>Just when I was worried I would never be able to have fun with computers again, along comes Plan 9 (well, technically 9Front, but it&amp;rsquo;s much of a muchness). What&amp;rsquo;s Plan 9? Do you care? It&amp;rsquo;s an operating system and you probably don&amp;rsquo;t, but you should.
As you can probably tell by this website&amp;rsquo;s recent theme update I was rather taken with Plan 9. It&amp;rsquo;s a quaint little operating system with a whole bunch of interesting ideas (distributed computing, amazing interoperation between the UI and the system, and the most fun you&amp;rsquo;ll ever have with window management).</description></item><item><title>Alpine</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/alpine/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/alpine/</guid><description>For a good long while now I&amp;rsquo;ve been hosting a bunch of different services across different servers. Given that I started this tradition before I was particularly proficient with GNU/Linux and *BSD, I have usually taken to using Ubuntu as a crutch of sorts. Now, there&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with Ubuntu per se, but it nearly always has more than I need preinstalled and removing software is a bigger risk than adding it.</description></item><item><title>Learning FreeBSD</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/learning-freebsd/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 18:00:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/learning-freebsd/</guid><description>As mentioned in an earlier post, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started hosting this site on a FreeBSD box to help me learn FreeBSD a little bit better and become a bit more bilingual with my UNIX-like systems. I had initially planned to install FreeBSD on my X200s, but unfortunately the OS was not supported by Libreboot, so I tabled the idea for a while.
The issue with this, of course, was that by limiting my use of FreeBSD to one very small server which had very little to do I would not really get to experience the benefits, drawbacks, and differences the system offered when compared with GNU and non-GNU Linux.</description></item><item><title>Into the Void</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</guid><description>Ever heard of Void Linux? Me neither until a little while ago. My friend had originally introduced me to Void when I was looking at going back to Arch Linux a few years ago, stating that it was (in many ways) a vastly superior system. I was intrigued, but I ultimately ended up sticking with Arch as I was familiar with it and was unwilling to give up on using the AUR at that point.</description></item><item><title>Getting on with Gutenberg</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/getting-on-with-gutenberg/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/getting-on-with-gutenberg/</guid><description>It seems like you can&amp;rsquo;t use anything these days without spending a good amount of time trying to keep up with changes to the product you&amp;rsquo;re using. My partner frequently complains about apps on her phone being updated, only to find that entire sections of the UI have changed with seemingly no warning. It is a frustration, to be sure, and following mailing lists, forums, and Slack (grr) groups to keep up with everything is an exhausting experience, but it is also something that is becoming more and more necessary as we enter the age of the rolling release.</description></item><item><title>Elementary OS Juno</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/elementary-juno/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/elementary-juno/</guid><description>Note: I have contributed translations to the Elementary OS project and have been an active Patreon supporter since April 2018. I don&amp;rsquo;t think of myself as particularly biased, but it&amp;rsquo;s best to mention these things
Summary (for those who don&amp;rsquo;t want to read) I like Elementary OS. It does plenty right and offers a minimalist system with decent keyboard control, a healthy environment which encourages users to invest in developers, and it largely keeps out of my way while offering the power of Ubuntu under the hood.</description></item><item><title>A reluctant return to Windows</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/reluctant-return/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/reluctant-return/</guid><description>I have lived a Windows-free life for a good long while now, using the OS only at work and leaving my home setup free of Microsoft’s influence. However, with the upcoming shift to Windows 10 in my place of work (which I will be helping to develop) and my need to study PowerShell and Hyper-V for my 70-410 exam, I decided to bite the bullet and once again load Windows 10 Professional on to my machine.</description></item></channel></rss>