<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>linux on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/linux/</link><description>Recent content in linux on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/linux/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Alpine</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/alpine/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/alpine/</guid><description>For a good long while now I&amp;rsquo;ve been hosting a bunch of different services across different servers. Given that I started this tradition before I was particularly proficient with GNU/Linux and *BSD, I have usually taken to using Ubuntu as a crutch of sorts. Now, there&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with Ubuntu per se, but it nearly always has more than I need preinstalled and removing software is a bigger risk than adding it.</description></item><item><title>Into the Void</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</guid><description>Ever heard of Void Linux? Me neither until a little while ago. My friend had orginally introduced me to Void when I was looking at going back to Arch Linux a few years ago, stating that it was (in many ways) a vastly superior system. I was intrigued, but I ultimately ended up sticking with Arch as I was familiar with it and was unwilling to give up on using the AUR at that point.</description></item><item><title>Goodbye, Guix</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/goodbye-guix/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/goodbye-guix/</guid><description>A fond farewell So for the last few weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been exclusively using GuixSD on my X200s. It&amp;rsquo;s been an interesting experiment, and there are a good many things I really liked about the system. For now, though, I am going back to Parabola.
Guix For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know, GNU Guix is a package manager which makes use of Guile to offer a really hackable and minutely controllable software management experience.</description></item><item><title>Elementary OS Juno</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/elementary-juno/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/elementary-juno/</guid><description>Note: I have contributed translations to the Elementary OS project and have been an active Patreon supporter since April 2018. I don&amp;rsquo;t think of myself as particularly biased, but it&amp;rsquo;s best to mention these things
Summary (for those who don&amp;rsquo;t want to read) I like Elementary OS. It does plenty right and offers a minimalist system with decent keyboard control, a healthy environment which encourages users to invest in developers, and it largely keeps out of my way while offering the power of Ubuntu under the hood.</description></item><item><title>Personal matters</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</guid><description>This post is more of a rant than anything technical. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s more of a moan born of recent frustrations. Nevertheless, this is my website. Where better to moan?
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started a new job working for a software company. My day-to-day work mostly includes rifling through SQL databases and making changes as well as searching for causes of issues faced by customers. This job has me using a work-issued MacBook Air and a copy of Windows 10 running in a virtual machine.</description></item><item><title>Back to the drawing board</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/back-to-the-drawing-board/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/back-to-the-drawing-board/</guid><description>For the past couple of weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying out new things. New to me, anyway. And as you might expect, I&amp;rsquo;m really bad at them. Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about that!
Why did it have to be Moodle? I work in a very Microsoft-centric environment. The vast majority of our servers are Windows 2016, 2012 R2, and a few straggling 2008 R2 boxes which just refuse to die. Possibly for this reason, we&amp;rsquo;ve never had a GNU/Linux technician.</description></item><item><title>A reluctant return to Windows</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/reluctant-return/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/reluctant-return/</guid><description>I have lived a Windows-free life for a good long while now, using the OS only at work and leaving my home setup free of Microsoft’s influence. However, with the upcoming shift to Windows 10 in my place of work (which I will be helping to develop) and my need to study PowerShell and Hyper-V for my 70-410 exam, I decided to bite the bullet and once again load Windows 10 Professional on to my machine.</description></item></channel></rss>