<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>lisp on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/lisp/</link><description>Recent content in lisp on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/lisp/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Roswell for everyone!</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/roswell-for-everyone/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/roswell-for-everyone/</guid><description>This website uses coleslaw as a static site generator. Coleslaw is managed using Roswell. Some of my bots are written in lisp and packaged using Roswell. It&amp;rsquo;s safe to say I like Roswell.
As mentioned a little while ago I&amp;rsquo;ve been teaching myself how to write FreeBSD ports. Since I run this site on a FreeBSD box, it is only logical that I would try to package the tools I&amp;rsquo;m using.</description></item><item><title>Building smarter</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/building-smarter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 02:23:40 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/building-smarter/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to improve the way I deploy this website for a little while now. Since I stopped using Netlify in favour of a more bare-bones approach, there has been a lot of manual/ugly work involved with the process of updating this website and posting from its RSS feed to my Mastodon feed.
Initially, I simply cloned the git repository for this site to my FreeBSD box and then SSHd in to the box to pull the lates files.</description></item><item><title>Playing with ports</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/playing-with-ports/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 22:38:36 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/playing-with-ports/</guid><description>As mentioned in my previous post, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been playing around with FreeBSD on one of my laptops. Why? Boredom, frankly. Boredom with my job, boredom with my lack of social life, boredom with the weather. Whatever the cause, the cure is always computer fun!
If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever used FreeBSD you&amp;rsquo;re probably already well aware of the ports sytem. It&amp;rsquo;s the thing that scares people because you mentioned the dreaded &amp;ldquo;S&amp;rdquo; word</description></item><item><title>Coleslaw migration</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/coleslaw-migration/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/coleslaw-migration/</guid><description>This marks my third(?) migration to a new site format! 🎉
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started learning to use Emacs after leaving the Emacs manual lying around for the better part of a year. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to try my hand at some common lisp I figured it would be a good time to start learning, and my goodness I wish I&amp;rsquo;d started this sooner.
As part of this new experience I started looking into ways I could use Lisp in my everyday life.</description></item></channel></rss>