<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>computer on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/computer/</link><description>Recent content in computer on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:28:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/computer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dell XPS 13 thoughts</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/xps-13-thoughts/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:28:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/xps-13-thoughts/</guid><description>So I decided finally (finally!) that I was going to invest in a new device in preparation for my upcoming move to Germany. I&amp;rsquo;ve never really been much of a hardware person, if I&amp;rsquo;m honest. Hardware has always just been a means to an end to get me working with software as efficiently as possible be it productivity software, games, or media software. For this reason my computers have always been a bit off the mark; I will nearly always pick something over-specced or under-specced, something too big or something too small, etc.</description></item><item><title>Into the Void</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</guid><description>Ever heard of Void Linux? Me neither until a little while ago. My friend had originally introduced me to Void when I was looking at going back to Arch Linux a few years ago, stating that it was (in many ways) a vastly superior system. I was intrigued, but I ultimately ended up sticking with Arch as I was familiar with it and was unwilling to give up on using the AUR at that point.</description></item><item><title>Personal matters</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</guid><description>This post is more of a rant than anything technical. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s more of a moan born of recent frustrations. Nevertheless, this is my website. Where better to moan?
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started a new job working for a software company. My day-to-day work mostly includes rifling through SQL databases and making changes as well as searching for causes of issues faced by customers. This job has me using a work-issued MacBook Air and a copy of Windows 10 running in a virtual machine.</description></item></channel></rss>