<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>work on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/work/</link><description>Recent content in work on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/work/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Hunt</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/the-hunt/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/the-hunt/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to live abroad since I was a very young child. As a beady-eyed youngster I distinctly remember telling my parents I was going to be a vet out in Japan working at the base of mount Fuji. Obviously, at that age I had no idea the logistical challenges such a move would bring. Even if I were to study veterinary medicine and Japanese simultaneously, I very much doubt there would be any appetite for a practice opening at the base of a mountain.</description></item><item><title>Finally, change</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/finally-change/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/finally-change/</guid><description>Some big life changes The last time I posted anything here was August 2020. Wow. That&amp;rsquo;s a pretty substantial break, but it does also coincide with the last time I had any time off work. So in a way it makes sense.
A lot has happened since then, but the biggest thing for me personally is that I have taken a job opportunity out in Germany. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to get out of the UK for a while now, so to have finally managed to secure an opportunity is pretty huge for me.</description></item><item><title>Acclimitising to new tech</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/acclimitising-to-new-tech/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/acclimitising-to-new-tech/</guid><description>My team recently moved away from a (frankly old and creaking) ManageEngine ServiceDesk solution to Jira for our Helpdesk. This has been met mostly with dismay by the majority of my team, so much so that I am one of the only people in the office still excited about the upgrade. As always, there were teething issues during the initial upgrade, but a few months on everything is more or less stable and we have lots of ideas for how to evolve the product.</description></item></channel></rss>