<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>website on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/website/</link><description>Recent content in website on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 03:39:15 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/website/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>More speed improvements</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-speed/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 03:39:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-speed/</guid><description>A little while ago I made some significant changes to this website&amp;rsquo;s design, asset delivery, and build system. Recently, however, I decided to do some benchmarking against a friend&amp;rsquo;s site to see how it stacked up and I was surprised to see that my site was still significantly slower than it could be, and it was also failing some Lighthouse tests when run through Chromium. I decided to take the time to fix these recently and have madethe following changes:</description></item><item><title>Site speed improvements</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/site-speed-improvements/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/site-speed-improvements/</guid><description>I got poking around at this site and was doing some thinking. Mainly along the lines of speed and security. By default, the dark-hyde theme provided by the good folks over at Coleslaw uses Google&amp;rsquo;s CDN for font delivery. This is all well and good, however I&amp;rsquo;m really not a big fan of Google at all and like to avoid them where possible. With that in mind, I started thinking about how I could go about replacing them.</description></item><item><title>Building smarter</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/building-smarter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 02:23:40 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/building-smarter/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to improve the way I deploy this website for a little while now. Since I stopped using Netlify in favour of a more bare-bones approach, there has been a lot of manual/ugly work involved with the process of updating this website and posting from its RSS feed to my Mastodon feed.
Initially, I simply cloned the git repository for this site to my FreeBSD box and then SSHd in to the box to pull the lates files.</description></item><item><title>Coleslaw migration</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/coleslaw-migration/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/coleslaw-migration/</guid><description>This marks my third(?) migration to a new site format! 🎉
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started learning to use Emacs after leaving the Emacs manual lying around for the better part of a year. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to try my hand at some common lisp I figured it would be a good time to start learning, and my goodness I wish I&amp;rsquo;d started this sooner.
As part of this new experience I started looking into ways I could use Lisp in my everyday life.</description></item><item><title>Moving to Sphinx</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/moving-to-sphinx/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/moving-to-sphinx/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve made a few changes to this website. Well, not really a few changes, more like a complete overhaul. I was getting a bit bored of using Hugo/Markdown and decided to challenge myself to the following:
Move to Sphinx Enable Ablog Move away from Github to Gitlab Get Netlify CI working with the new setup This wasn&amp;rsquo;t too difficult in theory, more time consuming (what can I say? I get bored).</description></item><item><title>More writing</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-writing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-writing/</guid><description>And now for something completely different I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing posts on this website for a little while now, mostly relating to my technological exploits and sysadmin misadventures. While this is a big part of my life at the moment, it&amp;rsquo;s not the only thing I do. I&amp;rsquo;m going to try and write a bit more about non-technology things just to try to encourage myself to focus on other things alongside computers.</description></item></channel></rss>