<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tech on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/tech/</link><description>Recent content in tech on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:28:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/tech/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dell XPS 13 thoughts</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/xps-13-thoughts/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:28:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/xps-13-thoughts/</guid><description>So I decided finally (finally!) that I was going to invest in a new device in preparation for my upcoming move to Germany. I&amp;rsquo;ve never really been much of a hardware person, if I&amp;rsquo;m honest. Hardware has always just been a means to an end to get me working with software as efficiently as possible be it productivity software, games, or media software. For this reason my computers have always been a bit off the mark; I will nearly always pick something over-specced or under-specced, something too big or something too small, etc.</description></item><item><title>Finally, change</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/finally-change/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/finally-change/</guid><description>Some big life changes The last time I posted anything here was August 2020. Wow. That&amp;rsquo;s a pretty substantial break, but it does also coincide with the last time I had any time off work. So in a way it makes sense.
A lot has happened since then, but the biggest thing for me personally is that I have taken a job opportunity out in Germany. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to get out of the UK for a while now, so to have finally managed to secure an opportunity is pretty huge for me.</description></item><item><title>In defence of GNOME Web</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/in-defence-of-gnome-web/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/in-defence-of-gnome-web/</guid><description>So you probably already know that Mozilla recently went bang and fired 25% of its workforce before announcing that whoops lol actually we are still going to be able to feed the hungry fox this year. Among the teams affected were the servo developers, a lot of the threat response team, and (I believe) the entirety of the team behind MDN: the only good resource for web development don&amp;rsquo;t @ me.</description></item><item><title>Plan 9 fun</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/plan-9-fun/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/plan-9-fun/</guid><description>Just when I was worried I would never be able to have fun with computers again, along comes Plan 9 (well, technically 9Front, but it&amp;rsquo;s much of a muchness). What&amp;rsquo;s Plan 9? Do you care? It&amp;rsquo;s an operating system and you probably don&amp;rsquo;t, but you should.
As you can probably tell by this website&amp;rsquo;s recent theme update I was rather taken with Plan 9. It&amp;rsquo;s a quaint little operating system with a whole bunch of interesting ideas (distributed computing, amazing interoperation between the UI and the system, and the most fun you&amp;rsquo;ll ever have with window management).</description></item><item><title>Ditch the walled gardens</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/walled-gardens/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/walled-gardens/</guid><description>A couple of years ago, I cancelled my Spotify subscription. In fact, I completely discontinued my use of the platform. My reasoning at the time seemed petty, but everything I&amp;rsquo;ve learned and listened to since has convinced me that this was the right way to go.
Back in those days, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really have a problem with Spotify. I am a musician myself, so I wanted to contribute to my favourite musicians even though I lacked the funds to buy every new album.</description></item><item><title>Site speed improvements</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/site-speed-improvements/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/site-speed-improvements/</guid><description>I got poking around at this site and was doing some thinking. Mainly along the lines of speed and security. By default, the dark-hyde theme provided by the good folks over at Coleslaw uses Google&amp;rsquo;s CDN for font delivery. This is all well and good, however I&amp;rsquo;m really not a big fan of Google at all and like to avoid them where possible. With that in mind, I started thinking about how I could go about replacing them.</description></item><item><title>Alpine</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/alpine/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/alpine/</guid><description>For a good long while now I&amp;rsquo;ve been hosting a bunch of different services across different servers. Given that I started this tradition before I was particularly proficient with GNU/Linux and *BSD, I have usually taken to using Ubuntu as a crutch of sorts. Now, there&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with Ubuntu per se, but it nearly always has more than I need preinstalled and removing software is a bigger risk than adding it.</description></item><item><title>Building smarter</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/building-smarter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 02:23:40 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/building-smarter/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to improve the way I deploy this website for a little while now. Since I stopped using Netlify in favour of a more bare-bones approach, there has been a lot of manual/ugly work involved with the process of updating this website and posting from its RSS feed to my Mastodon feed.
Initially, I simply cloned the git repository for this site to my FreeBSD box and then SSHd in to the box to pull the lates files.</description></item><item><title>weeabot</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/weeabot/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/weeabot/</guid><description>So I&amp;rsquo;ve been having some fun recently trying to teach myself Rust. I&amp;rsquo;m not really a programmer by any stretch of the imagination (yet!) but was challenged to write a bot for a Matrix chatroom I frequent. Most of us have written bots already, so it was my time to try something.
Originally I had planned to use Python like I had done previously for my Mastodon bot, tsukumogami. However, I&amp;rsquo;d been hearing some interesting things about Rust and decided it would be a fun challenge to try and write something functional in the language.</description></item><item><title>Say no to Slack</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/say-no-to-slack/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/say-no-to-slack/</guid><description>My workplace uses Slack. Actually, let me rephrase that: some of my coworkers use Slack. The company for which I work has had some trouble committing properly to a communications platform, which has left us in something of a state of limbo when it comes to communicating with one another. Some people only use Slack, others only Skype, still more refuse to communicate by anything other than good old fashioned face-to-face or email.</description></item><item><title>Going free</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/going-free/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/going-free/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with and enjoying technology most of my life. As such (and given the long history of vendor lock-in and associated cost/challenge with going without the support of major tech companies), I have a pretty significant footprint with certain tech companies. I&amp;rsquo;ve been with Google/Gmail/Android for many years. I have files stored up on Onedrive and Google Cloud. I have been working with Windows, ChromeOS, and even macOS and iOS at various stages as long as I have been working with computers.</description></item><item><title>Into the Void</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</guid><description>Ever heard of Void Linux? Me neither until a little while ago. My friend had orginally introduced me to Void when I was looking at going back to Arch Linux a few years ago, stating that it was (in many ways) a vastly superior system. I was intrigued, but I ultimately ended up sticking with Arch as I was familiar with it and was unwilling to give up on using the AUR at that point.</description></item><item><title>Matrix is here</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/matrix-is-here/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/matrix-is-here/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about it before… And it&amp;rsquo;s finally here! After much head scratching, frustration, and eventually the building of an entirely new server, my Matrix server garappa.chat is up and running. This has been something I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about doing for a while as I try to get away from all bigger services in favour of hosting my own. While Mastodon and Funkwhale where considerably easier to set up, I have a feeling it will be worth it in the end.</description></item><item><title>Tanuki Tunes update</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/tanuki-tunes-update/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/tanuki-tunes-update/</guid><description>Another Funkwhale update After a little bit of frustration on my side due to not following the directions properly, Tanuki Tunes is now running Funkwhale 0.18.1. The changes in this version will be mostly invisible to end-users, but include important bugfixes such as one that prevented the editing of tracks in the Django admin panel. This update has also made me aware that the site was previously running an out-of-date version of Postgresql.</description></item><item><title>Baku Social news</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/baku-social-news/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/baku-social-news/</guid><description>Technical updates So it&amp;rsquo;s been a bit of a busy month for Baku Social. The server experienced some minor downtime at the end of December owing to high memory usage, however there doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have been anything breeching the limits since then so fingers crossed there is no need yet to upgrade the specs of the VPS itself. I&amp;rsquo;m continuing to monitor it to ensure that nothing goes overboard, but given the low traffic both it and Tanuki Tunes seem to be managing fine for the moment.</description></item><item><title>Baku Social</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/baku-social/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/baku-social/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been looking for a project recently to teach me some more about various technologies, specifically public cloud stuff like AWS and container tech like Docker. I have been looking to get into this stuff for a little while and even previously hosted on of my blogs on a container OS, but that was shortlived due to too many headaches with Wordpress containers. For the last few months I had also been looking for a way to replace Spotify – which I had left behind due to privacy concerns, costs, and library limitations (I listen to some… weird stuff).</description></item><item><title>Getting on with Gutenberg</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/getting-on-with-gutenberg/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/getting-on-with-gutenberg/</guid><description>It seems like you can&amp;rsquo;t use anything these days without spending a good amount of time trying to keep up with changes to the product you&amp;rsquo;re using. My partner frequently complains about apps on her phone being updated, only to find that entire sections of the UI have changed with seemingly no warning. It is a frustration, to be sure, and following mailing lists, forums, and Slack (grr) groups to keep up with everything is an exhausting experience, but it is also something that is becoming more and more necessary as we enter the age of the rolling release.</description></item><item><title>Apple: drink the cider</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/apple-drink-cider/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/apple-drink-cider/</guid><description>Let me get this off my chest right now. I hate Apple. I hate iOS. I hate macOS. I hate the software, the hardware, and the ethos of Apple. To my mind, Apple represents the very worst of the technology industry: devices which are hard to use, easy to break, and difficult to fix. Therefore, I&amp;rsquo;m never surprised when I see news stories like this one.
The long and short of this story is that Apple have implemented a new chip (the T2 chip) which can detect whether or not repairs to a broken machine have been carried out by a verified technician using a pre-configured pin code.</description></item><item><title>Personal matters</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</guid><description>This post is more of a rant than anything technical. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s more of a moan born of recent frustrations. Nevertheless, this is my website. Where better to moan?
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started a new job working for a software company. My day-to-day work mostly includes rifling through SQL databases and making changes as well as searching for causes of issues faced by customers. This job has me using a work-issued MacBook Air and a copy of Windows 10 running in a virtual machine.</description></item><item><title>New site</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-site/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-site/</guid><description>As the astute among you may have noticed, this site has undergone some changes over the last couple of days. That&amp;rsquo;s because I&amp;rsquo;ve now completely moved away from Wordpress and destroyed my old server in favour of a different provider.
There are a couple of reasons for this:
The server was costing me money that I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to spare Wordpress is slow and cumbersome. Even a simple site like this was taking far too long to load I wasn&amp;rsquo;t learning anything by using Wordpress This last point is the reason I&amp;rsquo;ve moved to the solution I have.</description></item><item><title>Deploying and controlling Google Chrome settings using Microsoft Intune</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/deploying-controlling-chrome-intune/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/deploying-controlling-chrome-intune/</guid><description>Righto. This one has given me a mild headache for the last couple of days, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found a workable solution that allows me to set a home page for users in Chrome. You would have thought that would be really easy, right? Well, Google in its infinite wisdom has decided that conventional Windows management is for wusses. So down the rabbit hole we go.
Ingesting ADMX templates Let us say, for the sake of argument, that you have deployed the Chrome Enterprise .</description></item><item><title>Microsoft Teams deployment headaches</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/teams-deployment-headaches/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/teams-deployment-headaches/</guid><description>So you want to use Microsoft Teams in your organisation, huh? Are you prepared for the pain? The lack of documentation? The feeling of utter exasperation at a company unable to properly consider the needs of enterprise customers in their new &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; approach? Well, I&amp;rsquo;m here to share my experiences with you so that hopefully you can avoid some of the pain I had to go through in getting this all ready for our upcoming rollout.</description></item><item><title>Back to the drawing board</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/back-to-the-drawing-board/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/back-to-the-drawing-board/</guid><description>For the past couple of weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying out new things. New to me, anyway. And as you might expect, I&amp;rsquo;m really bad at them. Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about that!
Why did it have to be Moodle? I work in a very Microsoft-centric environment. The vast majority of our servers are Windows 2016, 2012 R2, and a few straggling 2008 R2 boxes which just refuse to die. Possibly for this reason, we&amp;rsquo;ve never had a GNU/Linux technician.</description></item><item><title>Some more Windows work</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/some-more-windows-work/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/some-more-windows-work/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s been a little while since I last posted here. I&amp;rsquo;ve been having a very busy and productive time at work. Let&amp;rsquo;s jump in to some of the stuff I&amp;rsquo;ve learned over the past couple of weeks. Come on! It&amp;rsquo;ll be fun!
Or not. Who knows? More importantly, who cares what you think? It&amp;rsquo;s my blog and I WILL cry when I want to.
It&amp;rsquo;s all about the cloud As we all know, Cloud services are the way absolutely everything on God&amp;rsquo;s green bloody earth are going these days.</description></item><item><title>Knit and Perl</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/knit-and-perl/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/knit-and-perl/</guid><description>A Fun Experiment I mostly seem to hang out with coders. It seems that the people with whom I most frequently interact are computer scientists or software developers. I don’t really know why, other than they are the only people crazy enough to use Riot for their day-to-day communications and chatroom facility. For this reason, I’m surrounded by programming with little to no comprehension of what is going on the majority of the time.</description></item><item><title>PGP problems promise pounding headaches</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/pgp-problems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/pgp-problems/</guid><description>Let’s clear up some FUD At the moment, information on this flaw is scarce, so as always it’s best to wait until the paper is published (which EFF says will be done at 07:00 UTC on May 15th). However, there are some things we can clear up from the start.
Firstly, it does not look like this is a flaw with PGP itself, but rather with implementations of GPG used in email programs such as Enigmail.</description></item><item><title>A reluctant return to Windows</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/reluctant-return/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/reluctant-return/</guid><description>I have lived a Windows-free life for a good long while now, using the OS only at work and leaving my home setup free of Microsoft’s influence. However, with the upcoming shift to Windows 10 in my place of work (which I will be helping to develop) and my need to study PowerShell and Hyper-V for my 70-410 exam, I decided to bite the bullet and once again load Windows 10 Professional on to my machine.</description></item><item><title>Acclimitising to new tech</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/acclimitising-to-new-tech/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/acclimitising-to-new-tech/</guid><description>My team recently moved away from a (frankly old and creaking) ManageEngine ServiceDesk solution to Jira for our Helpdesk. This has been met mostly with dismay by the majority of my team, so much so that I am one of the only people in the office still excited about the upgrade. As always, there were teething issues during the initial upgrade, but a few months on everything is more or less stable and we have lots of ideas for how to evolve the product.</description></item><item><title>Another day, another Intel fail</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/intel-fail/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/intel-fail/</guid><description>A few years ago, I&amp;rsquo;d have been shocked to see the sort of vulnerabilities I see announced these days once a year, let alone once a month. But the rise of cybersecurity as a respected industry has led to the big companies such as Microsoft, Apple, Canonical, etc. pulling up their socks and crushing vulnerabilities in a timely manner. This is all great, except for those of us whose job it is to deploy these fixes.</description></item><item><title>Deploying Sophos in a production environment</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/deploying-sophos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/deploying-sophos/</guid><description>AntiVirus is a necessary evil. With the world more connected than ever before, every device needs protection and tools to allow administrators oversight. Currently, the AV I work with is Sophos; cloud-based solution for Windows, Mac, and Linux. When I was working on the frontline, I quickly became aware that Sophos did not deploy during imaging as it had initially done, nor could it easily be pushed out via SCCM. We spent a long time going around to each freshly imaged machine and loading Sophos on, rebooting the machine, and logging tickets to have its policy applied.</description></item><item><title>Uncontrolled devices: not even once</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/uncontrolled-devices/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/uncontrolled-devices/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m a systems administrator by trade (or as I often find myself writing, a “systemd administrator” since that cancerous piece of bloatware consumes most of my troubleshooting life). It is, therefore, perhaps unsurprising that I like having control over the devices in my home. I refuse to use Apple devices apart from the one I have to use for work, I allow only GNU/Linux devices to be used on our home WiFi, and while my rooted Android phone is still somewhat lacking in end-user control, I plan to replace it with the Librem 5 when it launches.</description></item></channel></rss>