<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>social on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/social/</link><description>Recent content in social on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/social/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Baku Social news</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/baku-social-news/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/baku-social-news/</guid><description>Technical updates So it&amp;rsquo;s been a bit of a busy month for Baku Social. The server experienced some minor downtime at the end of December owing to high memory usage, however there doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have been anything breeching the limits since then so fingers crossed there is no need yet to upgrade the specs of the VPS itself. I&amp;rsquo;m continuing to monitor it to ensure that nothing goes overboard, but given the low traffic both it and Tanuki Tunes seem to be managing fine for the moment.</description></item><item><title>Baku Social</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/baku-social/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/baku-social/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been looking for a project recently to teach me some more about various technologies, specifically public cloud stuff like AWS and container tech like Docker. I have been looking to get into this stuff for a little while and even previously hosted on of my blogs on a container OS, but that was shortlived due to too many headaches with Wordpress containers. For the last few months I had also been looking for a way to replace Spotify – which I had left behind due to privacy concerns, costs, and library limitations (I listen to some… weird stuff).</description></item></channel></rss>