<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>rant on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/rant/</link><description>Recent content in rant on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/rant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ditch the walled gardens</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/walled-gardens/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/walled-gardens/</guid><description>A couple of years ago, I cancelled my Spotify subscription. In fact, I completely discontinued my use of the platform. My reasoning at the time seemed petty, but everything I&amp;rsquo;ve learned and listened to since has convinced me that this was the right way to go.
Back in those days, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really have a problem with Spotify. I am a musician myself, so I wanted to contribute to my favourite musicians even though I lacked the funds to buy every new album.</description></item><item><title>Say no to Slack</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/say-no-to-slack/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/say-no-to-slack/</guid><description>My workplace uses Slack. Actually, let me rephrase that: some of my coworkers use Slack. The company for which I work has had some trouble committing properly to a communications platform, which has left us in something of a state of limbo when it comes to communicating with one another. Some people only use Slack, others only Skype, still more refuse to communicate by anything other than good old fashioned face-to-face or email.</description></item><item><title>Bring back my internet</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/bring-back-my-internet/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/bring-back-my-internet/</guid><description>Mixed messages Okay, so I&amp;rsquo;m slightly reneging on my earlier post by writing about computers again, but trust me when I say this one is as much personal as it is technical.
Back in t' day It seems so bizarre to me that people are taken aback by my not having a Facebook account. Or a Twitter account. Or anything that they have bar email.
I&amp;rsquo;ll add you on Facebook.</description></item><item><title>Apple: drink the cider</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/apple-drink-cider/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/apple-drink-cider/</guid><description>Let me get this off my chest right now. I hate Apple. I hate iOS. I hate macOS. I hate the software, the hardware, and the ethos of Apple. To my mind, Apple represents the very worst of the technology industry: devices which are hard to use, easy to break, and difficult to fix. Therefore, I&amp;rsquo;m never surprised when I see news stories like this one.
The long and short of this story is that Apple have implemented a new chip (the T2 chip) which can detect whether or not repairs to a broken machine have been carried out by a verified technician using a pre-configured pin code.</description></item><item><title>Personal matters</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</guid><description>This post is more of a rant than anything technical. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s more of a moan born of recent frustrations. Nevertheless, this is my website. Where better to moan?
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started a new job working for a software company. My day-to-day work mostly includes rifling through SQL databases and making changes as well as searching for causes of issues faced by customers. This job has me using a work-issued MacBook Air and a copy of Windows 10 running in a virtual machine.</description></item><item><title>Uncontrolled devices: not even once</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/uncontrolled-devices/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/uncontrolled-devices/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m a systems administrator by trade (or as I often find myself writing, a “systemd administrator” since that cancerous piece of bloatware consumes most of my troubleshooting life). It is, therefore, perhaps unsurprising that I like having control over the devices in my home. I refuse to use Apple devices apart from the one I have to use for work, I allow only GNU/Linux devices to be used on our home WiFi, and while my rooted Android phone is still somewhat lacking in end-user control, I plan to replace it with the Librem 5 when it launches.</description></item></channel></rss>