<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>blog on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/blog/</link><description>Recent content in blog on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 08:41:21 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Burnout</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/burnout/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 08:41:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/burnout/</guid><description>In December 2019, I was given a new role at work. This was with the understanding that there would need to be a transition period while I trained my replacement (I work with a very big, poorly documented product, which means that training is a very big task), but that I could expect to be out of my current role within 6 months.
7 months later, we have not even appointed somebody to the new role.</description></item><item><title>Site speed improvements</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/site-speed-improvements/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/site-speed-improvements/</guid><description>I got poking around at this site and was doing some thinking. Mainly along the lines of speed and security. By default, the dark-hyde theme provided by the good folks over at Coleslaw uses Google&amp;rsquo;s CDN for font delivery. This is all well and good, however I&amp;rsquo;m really not a big fan of Google at all and like to avoid them where possible. With that in mind, I started thinking about how I could go about replacing them.</description></item><item><title>Coleslaw migration</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/coleslaw-migration/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/coleslaw-migration/</guid><description>This marks my third(?) migration to a new site format! 🎉
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started learning to use Emacs after leaving the Emacs manual lying around for the better part of a year. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to try my hand at some common lisp I figured it would be a good time to start learning, and my goodness I wish I&amp;rsquo;d started this sooner.
As part of this new experience I started looking into ways I could use Lisp in my everyday life.</description></item><item><title>Into the Void</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/into-the-void/</guid><description>Ever heard of Void Linux? Me neither until a little while ago. My friend had originally introduced me to Void when I was looking at going back to Arch Linux a few years ago, stating that it was (in many ways) a vastly superior system. I was intrigued, but I ultimately ended up sticking with Arch as I was familiar with it and was unwilling to give up on using the AUR at that point.</description></item><item><title>Moving to Sphinx</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/moving-to-sphinx/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/moving-to-sphinx/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve made a few changes to this website. Well, not really a few changes, more like a complete overhaul. I was getting a bit bored of using Hugo/Markdown and decided to challenge myself to the following:
Move to Sphinx Enable Ablog Move away from Github to Gitlab Get Netlify CI working with the new setup This wasn&amp;rsquo;t too difficult in theory, more time consuming (what can I say? I get bored).</description></item><item><title>New developments</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-developments/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-developments/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s been a little while Every time I have a blog I am always really bad at posting to it consistently. Actually, a lot has changed in recent months so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d do a little brain dump.
Funkwhale Thanks to the lovely people at Funkwhale I&amp;rsquo;m finally getting involved properly with a software project. To date I&amp;rsquo;ve provided a couple of new (extremely simple) features and bugfixes, as well as leading a large project to restructure the documentation and provide a slew of new user guides.</description></item><item><title>Progress</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/progress/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/progress/</guid><description>Making a difference It feels good to actually have a positive impact on something. One of my biggest gripes about working in support is that you are – as a support agent – inevitably the face of disappoinment and/or failure at some point. The job is time and attention demanding, and sometimes you simply have to tell someone that things they want are not possible.
This is devastating for morale. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in all my support jobs: the tickets keep coming and all you can do is try to answer them all in SLA.</description></item><item><title>Bring back my internet</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/bring-back-my-internet/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/bring-back-my-internet/</guid><description>Mixed messages Okay, so I&amp;rsquo;m slightly reneging on my earlier post by writing about computers again, but trust me when I say this one is as much personal as it is technical.
Back in t' day It seems so bizarre to me that people are taken aback by my not having a Facebook account. Or a Twitter account. Or anything that they have bar email.
I&amp;rsquo;ll add you on Facebook.</description></item><item><title>More writing</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-writing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-writing/</guid><description>And now for something completely different I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing posts on this website for a little while now, mostly relating to my technological exploits and sysadmin misadventures. While this is a big part of my life at the moment, it&amp;rsquo;s not the only thing I do. I&amp;rsquo;m going to try and write a bit more about non-technology things just to try to encourage myself to focus on other things alongside computers.</description></item><item><title>New site</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-site/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-site/</guid><description>As the astute among you may have noticed, this site has undergone some changes over the last couple of days. That&amp;rsquo;s because I&amp;rsquo;ve now completely moved away from Wordpress and destroyed my old server in favour of a different provider.
There are a couple of reasons for this:
The server was costing me money that I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to spare Wordpress is slow and cumbersome. Even a simple site like this was taking far too long to load I wasn&amp;rsquo;t learning anything by using Wordpress This last point is the reason I&amp;rsquo;ve moved to the solution I have.</description></item></channel></rss>