<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>funkwhale on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/funkwhale/</link><description>Recent content in funkwhale on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>Unless otherwise credited all material &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a> by Ciarán Ainsworth</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/funkwhale/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ditch the walled gardens</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/walled-gardens/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/walled-gardens/</guid><description>A couple of years ago, I cancelled my Spotify subscription. In fact, I completely discontinued my use of the platform. My reasoning at the time seemed petty, but everything I&amp;rsquo;ve learned and listened to since has convinced me that this was the right way to go.
Back in those days, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really have a problem with Spotify. I am a musician myself, so I wanted to contribute to my favourite musicians even though I lacked the funds to buy every new album.</description></item><item><title>New developments</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-developments/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-developments/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s been a little while Every time I have a blog I am always really bad at posting to it consistently. Actually, a lot has changed in recent months so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d do a little brain dump.
Funkwhale Thanks to the lovely people at Funkwhale I&amp;rsquo;m finally getting involved properly with a software project. To date I&amp;rsquo;ve provided a couple of new (extremely simple) features and bugfixes, as well as leading a large project to restructure the documentation and provide a slew of new user guides.</description></item><item><title>Progress</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/progress/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/progress/</guid><description>Making a difference It feels good to actually have a positive impact on something. One of my biggest gripes about working in support is that you are – as a support agent – inevitably the face of disappoinment and/or failure at some point. The job is time and attention demanding, and sometimes you simply have to tell someone that things they want are not possible.
This is devastating for morale. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in all my support jobs: the tickets keep coming and all you can do is try to answer them all in SLA.</description></item><item><title>Bring back my internet</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/bring-back-my-internet/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/bring-back-my-internet/</guid><description>Mixed messages Okay, so I&amp;rsquo;m slightly reneging on my earlier post by writing about computers again, but trust me when I say this one is as much personal as it is technical.
Back in t' day It seems so bizarre to me that people are taken aback by my not having a Facebook account. Or a Twitter account. Or anything that they have bar email.
I&amp;rsquo;ll add you on Facebook.</description></item><item><title>More writing</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-writing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-writing/</guid><description>And now for something completely different I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing posts on this website for a little while now, mostly relating to my technological exploits and sysadmin misadventures. While this is a big part of my life at the moment, it&amp;rsquo;s not the only thing I do. I&amp;rsquo;m going to try and write a bit more about non-technology things just to try to encourage myself to focus on other things alongside computers.</description></item><item><title>Tanuki Tunes update</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/tanuki-tunes-update/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/tanuki-tunes-update/</guid><description>Another Funkwhale update After a little bit of frustration on my side due to not following the directions properly, Tanuki Tunes is now running Funkwhale 0.18.1. The changes in this version will be mostly invisible to end-users, but include important bugfixes such as one that prevented the editing of tracks in the Django admin panel. This update has also made me aware that the site was previously running an out-of-date version of Postgresql.</description></item><item><title>HKEP</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/hkep/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/hkep/</guid><description>This is a short EP I recorded back in 2015. It was inspired by my life in Hong Kong, where I had been studying at the time.
This EP is hosted on Tanuki Tunes!</description></item></channel></rss>