<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>personal on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/personal/</link><description>Recent content in personal on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 08:41:21 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/personal/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Burnout</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/burnout/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 08:41:21 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/burnout/</guid><description>In December 2019, I was given a new role at work. This was with the understanding that there would need to be a transition period while I trained my replacement (I work with a very big, poorly documented product, which means that training is a very big task), but that I could expect to be out of my current role within 6 months.
7 months later, we have not even appointed somebody to the new role.</description></item><item><title>New developments</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-developments/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/new-developments/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s been a little while Every time I have a blog I am always really bad at posting to it consistently. Actually, a lot has changed in recent months so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d do a little brain dump.
Funkwhale Thanks to the lovely people at Funkwhale I&amp;rsquo;m finally getting involved properly with a software project. To date I&amp;rsquo;ve provided a couple of new (extremely simple) features and bugfixes, as well as leading a large project to restructure the documentation and provide a slew of new user guides.</description></item><item><title>Progress</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/progress/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/progress/</guid><description>Making a difference It feels good to actually have a positive impact on something. One of my biggest gripes about working in support is that you are – as a support agent – inevitably the face of disappoinment and/or failure at some point. The job is time and attention demanding, and sometimes you simply have to tell someone that things they want are not possible.
This is devastating for morale. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in all my support jobs: the tickets keep coming and all you can do is try to answer them all in SLA.</description></item><item><title>Bring back my internet</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/bring-back-my-internet/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/bring-back-my-internet/</guid><description>Mixed messages Okay, so I&amp;rsquo;m slightly reneging on my earlier post by writing about computers again, but trust me when I say this one is as much personal as it is technical.
Back in t' day It seems so bizarre to me that people are taken aback by my not having a Facebook account. Or a Twitter account. Or anything that they have bar email.
I&amp;rsquo;ll add you on Facebook.</description></item><item><title>More writing</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-writing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/more-writing/</guid><description>And now for something completely different I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing posts on this website for a little while now, mostly relating to my technological exploits and sysadmin misadventures. While this is a big part of my life at the moment, it&amp;rsquo;s not the only thing I do. I&amp;rsquo;m going to try and write a bit more about non-technology things just to try to encourage myself to focus on other things alongside computers.</description></item><item><title>Personal matters</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/personal-matters/</guid><description>This post is more of a rant than anything technical. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s more of a moan born of recent frustrations. Nevertheless, this is my website. Where better to moan?
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started a new job working for a software company. My day-to-day work mostly includes rifling through SQL databases and making changes as well as searching for causes of issues faced by customers. This job has me using a work-issued MacBook Air and a copy of Windows 10 running in a virtual machine.</description></item></channel></rss>