<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>floss on Life inside a computer</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/tags/floss/</link><description>Recent content in floss on Life inside a computer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 22:38:36 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sporiff.github.io/tags/floss/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Playing with ports</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/playing-with-ports/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 22:38:36 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/playing-with-ports/</guid><description>As mentioned in my previous post, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been playing around with FreeBSD on one of my laptops. Why? Boredom, frankly. Boredom with my job, boredom with my lack of social life, boredom with the weather. Whatever the cause, the cure is always computer fun!
If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever used FreeBSD you&amp;rsquo;re probably already well aware of the ports system. It&amp;rsquo;s the thing that scares people because you mentioned the dreaded &amp;ldquo;S&amp;rdquo; word</description></item><item><title>Learning FreeBSD</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/learning-freebsd/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 18:00:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/learning-freebsd/</guid><description>As mentioned in an earlier post, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently started hosting this site on a FreeBSD box to help me learn FreeBSD a little bit better and become a bit more bilingual with my UNIX-like systems. I had initially planned to install FreeBSD on my X200s, but unfortunately the OS was not supported by Libreboot, so I tabled the idea for a while.
The issue with this, of course, was that by limiting my use of FreeBSD to one very small server which had very little to do I would not really get to experience the benefits, drawbacks, and differences the system offered when compared with GNU and non-GNU Linux.</description></item><item><title>Moving to FreeBSD</title><link>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/moving-to-freebsd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 22:09:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sporiff.github.io/posts/moving-to-freebsd/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been making some changes to my current website setup. Before, this site was hosted on the same server that currently hosts my Mastodon instance and Funkwhale pod, as well as my git server. But with gitea&amp;rsquo;s poor performance and the general overcrowding, mixed in with my recent winding down of my Streama server, I decided to make a completely new server for my website.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing a lot of playing around with FreeBSD lately as part of my never-ending quest to find the ideal operating system.</description></item></channel></rss>